BHARATH KUMAR REDDY GUNTAKA

Software Engineer with over 2.8+ years of real-time experience specializing in Java, SpringBoot(MVC), JavaScript, React. Collaborated to employ agile methods & excelling in RESTful API development. Demonstrated expertise in enhancing software products across diverse industries. Seeking full time opportunities to contribute & grow professionally in a fast-paced environment, to reach organization goals.

EDUCATION

Missouri University of Science & Technology, Missouri, US

Aug 2022-May 2024

3.6/4.0

Masters Of Science, Computer Science

Jun 2017-May2021

KL University, Vijayawada, AP, India

Bachelors of Technology, Computer Science and Engineering

3.2/4.0

TECHNICAL SKILLS

: Java, Python, SQL, HTML, CSS, Javascript, React, Python. **Programming Languages** : MongoDB, MYSQL, Hive, HBase, Pig, Spring data JPA, Neo4j. **Database**

: SDLC, Agile development model, OOPs, REST Api development, MVC. Methodologies

Software Tools & Technologies : Spring boot, Spring Security, Spring Kafka, Git, Jira, Bitbucket, Jenkins, Postman, Apache

tomcat, AWS, Big data- Hadoop & spark, JUnit Testing, Hibernate, Microservices, IOT.

Developer Tools : Vs Code, Eclipse, IntelliJ IDEA, STS, MySQL Workbench, Google Collab.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant at MUST, Missouri, US

Aug 2023–Dec 2024

Java and SQL database tutoring for tasks improvement, grading assignments, & guiding students in coding and queries. Collaborated on lesson plans, enhancing Java understanding of 72 students by 75%. Engaged with students to address queries & reinforce Java.

Software Developer at ACS Solutions, Hyderabad, India

Dec 2018–Jul 2022

- Spearheaded the development of reusable Sitecore components and React features, including custom hooks and route guards, enhancing application efficiency and user experience.
- Expertly utilized React ES6 and Redux for robust state management, significantly improving application scalability and maintainability.
- Engineered dynamic web applications leveraging ReactJS, Spring Boot, and Play Framework, focusing on high performance and responsive design.
- Demonstrated expertise in backend development with Spring Boot and Play Framework, creating efficient, scalable solutions.
- Crafted and optimized SQL and Neo4j queries, achieving optimal data manipulation and interaction for complex database operations.
- Ensured timely delivery of features and bug fixes, maintaining high-quality standards and minimizing side effects.
- Developed and automated new functionalities, enhanced existing features, and led API development and database integration, driving forward application capabilities.
- Played a key role in team leadership, aiding peers with technical queries and guiding project direction to meet strategic objectives.
- Enhanced team communication and client relations by delivering insightful presentations on project data, findings, and proposals, showcasing strong presentation skills.

PROJECTS

LinguaLink Chat Application, Full Stack Web Application, MUST - A dynamic chat application using Spring Boot for the backend and React for the frontend, featuring real-time text translation to empower seamless cross-lingual

Internal Fund Management System, Full Stack Web Application, ACS Solutions- A web-based application for managing a team's financial transactions, including tracking deposits and expenditures, to enhance financial transparency and efficiency.

Mole Master Challenge, Front-End Application- An engaging interactive game application where users earn points by accurately hitting randomly appearing moles on the screen, crafted to enhance user engagement and reflex testing.

Stickynotes - Created a user-friendly Sticky Notes web application using HTML and JavaScript, enabling users to easily create, organize, and manage their notes and tasks in a visually intuitive interface..

CERTIFICATIONS

- **AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner**
- Interactivity with JavaScript
- Introduction to HTML5
- Advanced Styling with Responsive Design